Hello, welcome everyone. It is June
25th, 2025.
We are in active inference gueststream
112.1
brainike variational inference with Hadi
Fifi. And I looked and found that
actually model stream 11.1 when we
discussed Pson variational autoenccoder
was on June 26th, 2024.
So just kind of funny that it's like
exactly 1 year or all but a day away
from a year. So, it's awesome to
check back in with you and hear these
research updates. So, thanks again for
joining and looking forward to the
presentation.
All right, awesome. Thanks, Daniel, for
the invitation. I had a great time last
time when I presented and um I hope we
can have fun this time again. All right,
so
so the the work that Daniel mentioned,
the Panag, it's I think this one. So,
you can check it out. It's uh from last
year and uh it it is published in uh
NERIPS last year and this is the new
preprint brain like variational
inference which we're going to talk
about today and that's a work uh in
collaboration with Decal who's a EXPS
PhD student um in Berkeley and uh Jake
who's my uh postto mentor
all right but you know in the title
there's like several words brain-like
variational inference and I hope that I
can um communicate what each of these
words mean to you by the end of this
talk and let's first start by inference.
What is inference? It's understanding
the world. So our brains receive sensory
information from the world out there and
we have to make sense of the state of
the world. We have to understand how the
world is right now so that we can act in
it and survive.
And in fact this is the topic of a new
blog post that I have written. I I'm
going to plug it here. Um so this blog
post is coming soon. It's probably like
in a week um on my website
mysterioustune.com.
Um and inference is you know I claim
that it's your brain trying to guess the
hidden cause of its observations.
And you know to just drive this point
home I I have I give you three very
concrete examples each more difficult
than the other. For example if you go
outside and see there is extensive
wetness of the ground you might guess
that you know there there was rain last
night. So the cause of what you observe
which is wet ground was rain. So that's
inference. You're actually doing
inference when you reach that conclusion
which is a very simple kind of
inference. Also um I uh discuss this
problem of degeneracy in visual
perception. Uh when you see a circular
shape it could be a 2D circle you know
held perfectly perpendicular to your
direction of gaze or it could be
actually a 3D sphere. And um you know
intuitively you might think that it's
most likely a sphere but how where does
that come from? That's your prior
knowledge. So um having lived in this
world we have seen more spheres than
circles. Therefore you might actually
intuitively think that what you're
seeing is actually a sphere. And um last
one is the most difficult um nearly
impossible type of inference is the
social inference. So when when some
somebody says something to you, you want
to understand what they actually meant
and um that is also uh can be understood
as an instance of inference. Um in
linguistics this is technically called
pragmatics, but I claim and um develop
an argument that all of these examples
are um you're basically performing
inference. And so I'm going to post this
um blog post in like a week or so. And
um you can either subscribe to the to
the website or follow me on social media
like Twitter and LinkedIn. I'm going to
post it there too.
Um here's another example from the blog
post. Um most of us here probably are
familiar with this allegory of the cave.
So Plato argued that being alive is just
like you know being prisoners in the
back of a cave. You know you're
separated from the real world out there.
This is the real world. You don't really
have access to it. But you see shadows
from the real world projected on the
wall that you have access to. And you
know when you see those shadows or
observations, you perform inference to
understand the likely causes that um
caused those observations. Well, in the
case of vision, those shadows are
probably just like, you know, the you
can think of them as photons originating
from real objects out there. And it's
your brain's job to interpret those
photons and build a 3D model of the
world from that. And that can be
understood as uh Beijian inference. And
this is an idea that um famously Hel
says perception as unconscious
inference. You know, it's it's the same
idea. You know, people um since 380 BC
have been thinking about it and we are
still thinking about it. You know,
that's that's what inference is. It's a
very broad thing that we have to
understand. But uh the point of the
paper is that okay this is inference and
this is a very um let's say a big
challenge that we have to deal with in
our lives and how does brain do it like
can how can you get um a brain-like
inference algorithm um especially from
first principles. So that's the idea. We
want to derive a brain-like inference
algorithm from first principles
you know because we want to understand
how does the brain perform this
inference al you know inference um task.
Okay that's the idea.
So just to summarize what is in the
paper um we start from this unifying
principle of variational free energy
minimization which is in you know
machine learning people more commonly uh
refer to free energy as evidence
lowerbound or elbow but it's the same
thing
and we're going to use that unifying
principle to derive different inference
algorithms as instances of free energy
minimization.
And this paper really is like a um half
synthesis review and half new algorithm.
For the synthesis part, we're going to
show that variational autoenccoders uh
predictive coding and sparse coding are
all instances of free energy
minimization.
And then we use that uh insight to
derive new architecture which is the
iterative plus on DAE um just by
starting from free energy minimization.
So that's a kind of a top- down
derivation of an algorithm. We don't put
anything there by hand. We just say like
look, we accept free energy minimization
as our principle and then we add some
other assumptions to it to derive this
algorithm. And I'm I'm going to be
explicit about all those assumptions.
Cuz you
like this bit better. Okay. All right.
Um so when we derive this algorithm we
also test uh whether it has any
empirical benefits because of course you
know it's it's very cool and it's very
theory driven but um we are also
interested in empirical benefits um and
and we explore convergence properties
sparity reconstruction trade-off and out
of domain generalization
um and and you know I'm going to explain
why each of these empirical benefits are
are interesting or important uh when we
get to that result but this is just the
summary of of the empirical results.
Okay. Now let's just talk about um
basian posterior inference. Um so
probably most of you are just familiar.
This is just a baze rule. Um what we
have on the left hand side is the
posterior. Uh if you remember from the
previous examples you could imagine like
x are the observations. This this could
be just an image like a retinal pattern
of photon whatever that you receive and
you want to infer what are the causes. Z
are the causes. So you want to compute
this probability distribution.
what is the likelihood of certain cog z
given that I have observed certain uh
observation x right and b tells us you
can compute it by um dividing this
likelihood times prior with the marginal
distribution
so this is fairly standard stuff so I'm
not going to linger too much here and
probably there are many interesting
videos on this you know this YouTube
channel that you can find to that
explains this idea um so I'm going to
move on uh but the point I want to make
here is that if you want to compute this
posterior distribution exactly you have
to go through this computing this
integral which is I just express this
marginal distribution as an integral
over all the possible causes uh where
this is just um you know the joint
distribution broken into this kind of
structure um and you know this is very
very difficult to compute first of all
most um in most cases there's no closed
form solution except you Like if you
have a very simple Gaussian distribution
for prior and likelihood then maybe you
can compute this but in most real world
cases you don't have access to that you
know close form solution and also it's
it's it's computationally hard to um
approximate as well like you have to go
through all the possible latent
configurations add them up you know to
to compute this therefore what I want to
you to um remember from this part is
that you know posterior inference
actually is a difficult uh task
computationally
Therefore, people have come up with
approximate u methods and one of them is
variational inference. So you introduce
some distribution Q and you call this
approximate posterior or variational
posterior and then you want to um you
want to use Q to approximate the actual
you know true posterior or optimal
posterior. How do you do it? By
minimizing the callback liler divergence
between Q and P. And this is just a very
standard test textbook level, you know,
introduction to to variational
inference. And again, I'm not going to
spend too much time. Uh this is just
very um standard stuff. Um and and
here's another uh this is the main
equation that we're going to work with.
And I think this is very important.
Therefore, I want to make sure that
we'll understand like every detail here.
Um in the paper in the appendix, we
derived this equation. So um if you
think if you haven't seen this before,
this is a very standard result in
variational inference. Uh and you can
see the paper appendix for a derivation.
Um but here let's just take this
equation as given. It's it's not a very
complicated derivation. It's a very
straightforward one. Uh but it it's
true. This equation holds for any
distribution Q that you know that is a
dist that is a proper uh density. Um so
let's let's actually try to understand
what this is. Okay, on the left hand
side we have the log of the marginal
distribution
uh p theta of x and then we have this
object here which is an expectation over
you know samples drawn from the
approximate posterior and this log ratio
of the joint distribution divided by the
approximate posterior and then this
thing is what we actually want to
minimize to find our um you know best
approximate posterior
and once One thing I I want to mention
here is that if you notice I have like
these colorcoded um things. So um in
this presentation and also in the paper
I'm using red to um to indicate the uh
inference components of the model and
blue to indicate the generative model uh
components.
And you know you can think of the blue
parameters as just you know theta as
parameters of the neural network that
you you know for the generative model.
Um or if you believe that the brain has
a generative model of the world, you can
think of theta as the synaptic weights
uh of the connections between neurons
and fi are just parameters that you have
to optimize to find the best Q.
And and for example, a very standard
example here is that if you have a
variational autoenccoder, PI and theta
are just both neural networks. And um
specifically you have for example uh Q
can be understood as a neural network
that takes any input X and outputs the
parameters that define this
distribution. Like for example if five
are neural network parameters you apply
that to X to get back the mean and
variance of a gausian if you think Q
should be a gausian. Okay. So but why
why is this equation interesting? Um
uh let me actually just show you this
visualization because I think this helps
us remember. So I told you this is model
evidence. So um that's evidence. You
have evidence lower bound or elbow and
then the KL divergence. So evidence plus
elbow is KL. Okay. And and why is this
equation interesting to us? Because
we're interested in inference. Um I want
you to take a look at the both left hand
side and right hand side of this
equation. If you notice there are no red
parameters on the left hand side. So you
know um the right hand side is the only
part of this equation that depends on
those red uh variational parameters fi
right. Therefore,
uh, intuitively, if you want to minimize
the KL, that's our goal. We defined good
inference like, um, you know, faithful
inference as just, um, a Q that is close
enough to P and, um, and and we define
that as, as, you know, a Q that
minimizes the KL. So minimizing this KL
term on the right hand side directly is
going to maximize elbow because the left
hand side doesn't depend on phi or if
you want to see like in algebraic form
you can just say if you compute the
derivative of this whole equation with
respect to phi this is going to vanish
there's no phi here is going to have 0
equals gradient of this elbow with
respect to phi plus gradient of kl with
respect to phi therefore another way to
see how minimum imizing KL is exactly
equivalent to maximizing elbow and and
this is the the the whole idea behind
you know maximizing elbow to do
inference which is you know elbow is
just negative free energy so that's
that's kind of one way of thinking about
free energy principle
okay so so this is a very important
equation I just wanted to spend quite
some time here um and and if there's any
questions maybe um we can actually turn
this into a kind of a discussion rather
than like keeping it to the end. Um and
you know I have happy to answer
questions if there are any.
All right. Now that we defined elbow and
we we know its utility, you know, we are
maximizing elbow because we're
interested in inference. Let's actually
just see what elbow looks like if we if
we expand it. Right? This is the
definition. And um one way to carve up
the elbow is this is the joint
distribution p theta x and z. You can
easily see that it can be broken into P
theta of X given Z. That's what this
term is. And then uh plus P theta of Z.
And again if you just um invert kind of
the the denominator and denominator it
turns out that this just looks like
another KL term which is very this is
different KL from the the previous one.
The previous one was between approximate
posterior and the true posterior. This
is between approximate posterior and the
prior. just an important uh distinction
and and there's you know different ways
to interpret this. This is just a
reconstruction term um which says if you
go from the latent cause and reconstruct
your observation um under your uh
posterior this should have high
likelihood. That's the intuition for
that. And this just ter you know it
appears from the math and the
interpretation is that you know you you
don't want to deviate too much from your
prior. This is a penalty. This is a
regularization penalty that um says
reconstruct your your your input as as
good as possible while not deviating too
much from your prior.
And and this has um a theoretical analog
in uh information theory where you can
think of this term as distortion. The
other term is rate and um Alex LM has a
really nice paper where where they um
make this rigorous. Okay, so this is so
far all of this is just standard you
know VAE
kind of uh theory, right? There's
there's nothing new so far. Uh but I
want to I want to highlight um you know
if you have if if you want to define
this elbow you have to you know uh make
decisions about three distinct
distributions. The first one is of
course the approximate posterior. uh you
have to choose what what form it has
like it could be gausian it could be
posson like our posan v paper from last
year and the likelihood also is a
distribution you have to you know choose
what it is and the prior as well so
there are three independent you know
choices you have to make
and here's a synthesis part of the paper
that we just say that look and this is
not new not all of this is known um but
we're just putting it nicely in in a
figure right uh we're saying look
variational free energy minimization
unifies all of these different models
across you know neuroscience and machine
learning and and this is the kind of a
taxonomy model tree that comes out of
that. So you have to first choose a
prior um let's say you choose Gausian
okay and then the next decision you're
faced with is what is your approximate
posterior if you choose direct delta you
actually recover predictive coding and
this you know if you want to uh I think
there's there's a video uh on this
channel that um goes through Baron
Millage review paper where they discuss
this um derivation so it's it's not it's
not new um but if you choose approximate
posterior to be Gaussian then you have
to also choose what your encoder is
right so if you choose um a neural
network that takes any image X and spits
out the parameters like you know it's a
gausian so you need to give me uh in
order to construct this Q you have to
give me like what is the mean and what
is the variance if you have a neural
network that produces those for you you
just recover variational autoenccoders
um king and bellon uh but if you if you
just don't do that If you do a iterative
inference procedure more like you know
neuroscience uh approaches like
predictive coding then you have
iterative gausing va which is just a
model we introduce in this paper
and and it's yes could I ask a few
questions on this slide yes go ahead
awesome okay so you have the prior can
be panon gaussian or lelause form so
what other edges could be coming out of
the prior or why would somebody select
one of those three forms that you have
listed here.
Okay. Yeah, I think this is not you know
definitely there are many more priors
that you can choose from. Um you know
there are other papers in the literature
that you can for example you can choose
a student t distribution for your prior
if you have if you think that your prior
should be heavy tailed and and certainly
there are other examples uh other than
these three. I'm just here using these
three to illustrate how different models
uh that that in in the leaves of this
tree can be um unified through this
unifying picture and and you're right
like what what really um like why would
you choose poson instead of gausian for
example that's our paper from last year
you would choose posson because if you
want your model to have representations
that are more brainlike um we know that
brain brain neurons in the brain, they
don't have continuous um unsigned uh
activations. They have they they
communicate through action potentials or
spikes and and panon is one way to model
that. Um or in the case of sparse
coding, the prior is chosen to be lost
because it has this like sparity
inducing property. Um so because you
might think that look my neurons neurons
in the brain, we have observed that
they're very sparsely active. Therefore,
loss is a better choice than gaussian
that that kind of that's the reasoning
that could go uh possible types of
reasoning that could go into your
choices.
Cool. And then one more and you may go
into this more. How is iterative
different than iteratively applying
amortized inference? Uh it's a very good
question. I think um here what I mean by
iterative is that you don't have any
neural networks. There's no free
parameters that you train for your
encoder. that's like fully iterative.
However, there are iterative amortized
hybrid models such as one from uh Joseph
Marino from 2018 where they actually do
exactly what you suggested. They have
they iteratively apply um some there's
some amortized neural network that
produces um parameters of your of your
distribution. there's another auxiliary
network that produces I think the the
gradients um I don't I don't exactly
remember but they they also had this
auxilary network was a pretty
complicated algorithm but um but you're
right that you know there might be um
hybrid cases where you have iterative
iteratively applied amortized neural
networks um to to get to the you know
final posterior
which by the way in the appendix of the
paper uh so so This paper is like I
don't know like 64 pages and we wanted
to make it self-contained. So the the
appendix actually contains all sorts of
you know u background information and
review of all these like existing
iterative amatize hybrid derative
amortize all all of that is in the paper
so you can take a look there if you're
curious.
Um I I just want to mention one thing
here is that um I didn't know about this
derivation like you know actually like
deriving sparse coding as LLAS plus
direct delta um posterior um I gave this
talk here at the Redwood Center for
theoretical neuroscience and Bruno Olsen
uh this same olden as here he was like
okay yeah this is cute but I I did this
derivation back in 96 I'll send it to
you. So he sent me this paper. It's not
even a paper. It's just a technical
report. It's like five pages. He was
inspired by Peter Dian's uh Helmo's
machine. Um and then he said, "Okay,
yeah, you can actually derive sparse
coding through this." Uh and I think
it's it's a pretty interesting paper,
but it's it's missing from the
literature. So I hope that this uh
citation will um you know, help fix that
kind of like it's it's every time you
site like direct direct delta posterior
with Gausian can give you like can give
you predictive coding from free energy
minimization. You can also site this
sparse coding which is like parallels
that but it's from 96. So it was a
pretty interesting revelation for me.
All right. Um the last one is like if
you choose posson for both prior and
approximate posterior and choose
amvertise you get the PVA paper which is
from the last year and now we just
replace the encoder with an iterative uh
procedure and we get iterative pulse on
VA and we're going to discuss why
iterative is like a little more brain
like than amortize and what are the
empirical benefits and all of that. Um
but yeah the whole point of this figure
is that you know really you can embrace
free energy minimization as just one
principle that can give you all sorts of
various algorithms and and and also we
um use this to just say like you you
know there's there's all sorts of
possibilities and you just make
different choices and you get wildly
different algorithms. So there's there's
a lot more left to explore here. That's
the one of the points. Just one short
comment on the distributions that you
have here.
Pan is waiting time. So it's always a
positive number like how much time until
the next bus appears. The appearance of
the bus is like the DRock delta because
it's a spike event
and then wait no no no I I wouldn't say
Pson is waiting time. I think Pson uh
you can actually construct a pson
process from those waiting times that
are exponentially distributed and and
Pson is the event count for a finite
observation window.
Thank you for the clarification. And
then Gaus in is just sort of the um the
the mother distribution
or the the the sort of central limit
theorem type large number convergence.
So it's helpful well behaved in a lot of
ways. But this is sort of like events
and their waiting time relationships,
right? Exactly. Like you're saying look
gausian. But by the way I one thing I
forgot to mention uh from previous slide
I I said there are three distributions
but right now I in this figure I have
only prior and approximate posterior
because the reason for that is for
literally all of these models uh the the
likelihood the the last third
distribution is always gausian in even
in the posson cases. So, and I think I
also like the idea of thinking about uh
the central limit theorem that that
could be like used to justify why your
observations um can be gausian
distributed.
Um and and yeah,
I I I guess that's it, right? You know,
you just think about your problem like
whatever you want to model. Um, in our
case, we want to model neural activity.
And you know, Gausian seems less
biologically plausible than integer spy
counts. But we're not saying that
integer spike counts is actually
literally what the brain is doing. We're
just saying that relative to Gausian,
it's a better choice which reflects
that, you know, discrete um eventbased
signaling that is ongoing in the brain.
That's the idea.
Okay.
All right. So in the paper we also talk
about prescriptive theories. Uh I want
to just use this opportunity to to uh
clarify what we mean by prescriptive.
This is just something that comes from
uh physics inspiration. So um another
thing that we're interested in is that
you know uh as when we go through the
paper I'm going to I'm going to talk
about inference which is a computation
and dynamics interchangeably. Like I'm
saying like look uh and this is like if
not you know we didn't come up with this
there's a fristen paper like a you know
free energy principle process theory
where they say like neural activity
dynamics can be understood as they're
just minimizing free energy. So so we're
interested in dynamics we're interesting
in deriving dynamical equations uh for
neurons and um that's where this
dynamics comes from. But but what is the
physics inspiration here? So in physics
you don't really put terms by hand like
if you want to come up with a dynamical
equation that describes a physical
system you usually don't you know u and
for example in in um effective field
theory um you start from the principle
of least action and then the
prescription here is that you just look
at the symmetries uh that your system
has to satisfy and that fully dictates
the entire lrangeian that you plug in to
this um action equation and you can
derive the dynamics from there. Um so so
this is pretty elegant, right? You don't
you don't put in terms by hand. You just
derive it from a top- down approach. You
just say like here's my my symmetries
and and it fully determines um what your
like branching should be. Of course, you
know, we don't have this much elegance
in in the messy world of Nur AI, but we
can do something roughly similar. So
we're we're saying look in our case our
principle is free energy minimization.
So we're saying this this object free
energy is is just you have to construct
it and you have to minimize it. That's
going to give you the dynamics. And then
the prescription is the kind of the
important part. Um in the paper we say
like if you choose these three things uh
poson distributions for your posterior
and online inference and natural
gradient descent on free energy you can
derive the architecture iterative pos
which which is a spiking recurren neural
network with stoastic leaky integrated
fire neurons and level competition and
you know I'll I'll I'll describe what
any of all of these mean um it's just um
it's just a framing like we we don't um
we we derive these things from from top
down principles. That's kind of the
emphasis here.
And um before going to actually like
show you the paper and the derivations
and the results, I want to show you
something very gimmicky that I I quite
like. So I don't know for for those of
you from from neuroscience background
you might have seen those videos of
hubil and visasel you know showing a bar
of light to an anesthetized cat and then
recording from the cat's visual cortex
and then there's like these these noises
that you can hear like that the neur
neurons are being activated by that bar
of light. So what I'm going to show you
here is a replication of those
experiments but from just a model neuron
and this neuron never saw neural
activity like never saw data from actual
neurons. What it did just like we
derived this um the algorithm from first
principles and we trained it on natural
image patches and then for example here
you see that in the top right um it it
learns receptive fields that look like
gabbors which is what you would observe
if you stick an electrod um to like a
primate visual cortex. Um, and what I'm
going to do is I'm going to just slide
this bar of light, the red bar here, uh,
across that receptive field. And I'm
going to here plot the firing rate of
this neuron in response to that. So the
y-axis is firing rate and also the
sample spike counts. It's a stochastic
spiking model. And x is time index.
Let's see if you can hear it.
One more time.
All right. So, I'm really excited about
this because, you know, this just uh
there's no
activity. There was just, you know, just
this algorithm was derived from from
just equations from top down. You know,
that's that's what excites me about
that. But anyway, here is where I
switched to paper PDF. Um, and I'm going
to walk you through the derivations
there. uh because I think the paper is
written uh and it you know decently uh
well um so it's easy to understand let's
do that and you see it
okay um yeah so it's the intro let's
just skip that um and and by the way you
can think of this as I'm going through
the PDF you can think of this as just
you know um a step-by-step guideline if
you wanted to read this paper on your
own this I think how you should do it.
So okay here you notice the notation um
we have this generative model uh defined
here and again the color coding
generative and and inference are always
blue and red and then we start from the
main equation and of course I have lots
of citations to the appendix here uh
where I provide all the necessary
information you don't you don't need to
read anything else just the appendix uh
for example here um just very quickly
this is the perceptionist inference more
like a philosophical and historical
background. Here I define what is
Beijian posterior inference and why is
it difficult um and this is this
equation is where I derive that elbow uh
equation that I had on the slides. So
it's um it's very um I think intuitive
as if you if you read it you'll see and
then here I say okay you need three
distributions for the elbow and then the
rest is just like carving up the elbow
you know gausian VAE what is it um how
do you exactly define a gausian VAE and
then going to pan which is our work from
last year here I discuss amortize versus
iterative inference and so on and then
this is my you know pedagogical like
intuitive derivation of a linear
predictive coding which of course the
more complete uh version is in in this
millillage uh review you can check it
out but yeah um and then finally
uh this is like a summary of the models
in this paper and also else from
elsewhere in this table and yeah so back
so so appendix A is just an extended
background and um that's all you need to
know to be able to understand this
paper.
But back to this. Okay, now we're back
at the main main paper um background
section.
Uh okay as you discussed you start from
elbow and then you recognize that
maximizing elbow is equivalent to
minimizing this KL term which is in our
case um which means you know you enhance
the quality of posterior inference by
maximizing elbow or minimizing free
energy which is exactly negative elbow.
So that's the key uh insight here that
you know you can connect theoretical
neuroscience to machine learning by
recognizing f is just negative elbow.
Next again just just to remind you we
have these three distributions we have
to choose and also the next choice we
have to make is um the the inference
method is it amortized or is it um then
we introduce VAE sparse coding and and
predictive coding as variational
inference. same figure as you just saw.
And importantly, um I I put this
derivation of the dynamics of a
predictive coding model because I'm
going to compare our result to this. And
we're going to find that in our case, we
get something a little more biologically
plausible than this standard predictive
coding dynamics. And I guess there's
there's no time for me to really go
through this. This is a very standard
result. it's you know it's an original
row ballot paper or any review papers
that that came after that. Um therefore
let's just keep this in mind. And this
is just the dynamics you derive from
standard predictive coding with Gausian
assumptions. And we're going to you know
when we derive our own iterative poson v
dynamics we're going to come back and
and and compare to this.
Okay. So um yeah here I I think there's
um several papers that we mentioned here
in this paragraph that are I think super
cool and interesting. So um if you're
interested you should check them out.
This paper is is is fascinating. Beijian
learning rule uh it was published I
think a couple years ago and they
basically say that you know you can um
any learning algorithm that has been
successful like including I don't know
um Adam dropout whatever SGD you can
actually uh cast them as instances of
variational inference so they start from
a variational objective and then they
show that if you just swap you know you
you choose your approximate posterior in
different ways and then you make some
additional uh uh like approximation
assumptions and look elsewhere. Um and
then you apply natural gradient descent
on that variational objective to derive
many many different learning rules as
instances of variational inference. So
this this is kind of this paper shows um
the unification potential of variational
inference in more like a optimization
machine learning uh type of land. Um so
you should check it out. It's very
interesting. Um and then later building
on DLR, this is a paper Jones Atal. It's
a Kevin Murphy paper. They introduce
Beijian online natural gradient. They
just say like if you want to do online
inference, you should do it using
natural gradient descent on the
variational objective. Um which is
exactly the same prescription following
PLR. They also do natural gradient
descent. And and just briefly, why
natural gradient descent? Because um you
know when we when we are optimizing the
posterior the posterior is a probability
distribution. It has its parameters are
um you know they don't live in uklidian
space. There's an intrinsic geometry
induced by the fissure metric and if you
don't respect that geometry you're going
to perform poorly. That's the intuition
which if you're interested you can
actually like there's a bunch of
citations in the paper that you can go
dig deeper. Um but following these two
uh very inspiring papers Bong and DLR
here is where we oh sorry where we
introduce our fond framework. So what
does it stand for? It's free energy
online natural gradient dynamics. So
we're interested in dynamics neural
dynamics. That's why we emphasize
dynamics. But you know u that's our
framework. We we're saying look if you
want to derive dynamics you know uh from
first principles just start from free
energy minimization and then um first
you have to identify the dynamical
variables like what are the things
you're optimizing what are the what how
do you parameterize your posterior
that's first choice you make and then
the temporal evolution of your posterior
parameters is fully determined by
natural gradient descent on variational
free energy that is our prescription
which will become concrete as we go
through the paper.
And and finally, we also embrace this
online update scheme um because that's
how brain performs inference, right? Um
just to give you an intuition what
online means here. Um so, so in most
machine learning cases, you have one one
single image, right? And you perform
inference on that single image to find
the posterior uh for that, right? But in
reality, the brain doesn't have like a a
prior that is fixed in the past and it
never changes and you always like have
images that you have to perform
inference. In in biological systems,
online inference makes a little more
sense um to to modeling how brains
perform inference. And online means that
your prior constantly gets updated as
time goes on. So you always have a a
moving prior that is being updated. And
um if you perform inference like let's
say you have a movie and there's a a new
frame comes in you perform inference you
get to the posterior and that posterior
at time t becomes the prior at time t +
one. That's what it means to have online
updated scheme. And I'll let me just
show you the figure real quick.
So if you start the these red curve is
just you know how your posterior
distribution is getting uh evolved in
time. Every single point on along this
curve is a posterior distribution.
And in the static inference you have
like one prior that is fixed in the
distant past t= 0 and you evolve in
time. You always compare back to that
prior. But in online inference your post
your prior itself gets updated and you
have always you compare your posterior
at t to the prior from the previous time
point which is also what bong does.
All right. Um that's it. So we're going
to use we're going to apply these
prescriptions and we're going to derive
a bunch of different VAE models
including the iterative posan one that
is um is going to give us interesting
theoretical and empirical results. Um so
let's go through that real quick.
Um okay
the first step we have to choose the
distributions right and as I mentioned
earlier when we were talking about that
uh you know the the the model tree uh
slide we choose pson because that's a
better approximation for like brain like
integer valued spike count
representations at least compared to
gausian poson is a little more brainlike
but here in appendix B1 we discussed
that you know we're not saying that the
brain is literally pulse on. We're
saying it's just a better approximation
um relative to Gausian.
And then for the likelihood, this is
what we go with. This is just simple
Gausian with a linear decoder. So you go
from latent observation latent cause Z.
So in our case these are just spike
counts and you multiply this linear
decoder layer fi um to that to get to
the mean of the gausian with some fixed
variance. This is like the simplest
possible case uh that we go with in this
like main paper but um we extend that to
more complicated cases in the appendix
including a nonlinear decoder and this
fi is actually called dictionary in
sparse coding literature. So it's the
same thing as a dictionary.
Okay. So
now let's talk about the prescriptive
choices like you know to to derive
dynamics from first principles. Um we
have to choose we have to address two
questions two additional questions. What
are the dynamical variables and what
equations govern their time um
evolution? And in appendix B2 I I
connect this again back to physics um uh
through this like prescriptive theories
in in physics. Um
for so okay
first question what are the dynamical
variables? So for for posson
the only par you know the only parameter
you have to give me so that I can
construct a pro you know a posson
distribution is the rate parameter the
firing rate but that's a positive value
and and the rate parameter itself is
very hard to optimize. Um therefore
we're going to make the following
choice. So we're going to say look we're
going to start with these real valued
vector U which is K is the number of
neurons and you have um U is you know
some real number and if you exponentiate
U you're going to get the firing rates
and you're going to be able to construct
uh poson distribution from those firing
rates and and this makes it easier
because you know u is um is a real
number you don't have to do constraint
optimization you can just you know do
natural gradient descent on on free
energy without having to constrain your
gradients so that it remains always
positive. That's like a pragmatic like a
mathematical convenience but also this
is not too biologically implausible
because you can actually interpret you
as membrane potentials.
So in you know from neuroscience we know
that neurons have this like local
private signal to them. There's their
membrane potential that fluctuates, goes
up and down and then if it reaches
certain threshold, neurons emit an
action potential or a spike. And there's
some work that shows that you can
actually model that relationship between
the membrane potential and the firing
rate through you know expansive
nonlinearities like like power laws or
exponential. Um so that's that's
basically two reasons why we chose this
parameterization mathematical
convenience and it's not biologically
too implausible
and once you choose that you have to um
you know you can just derive the
dynamics um through natural gradient
descent on variational free energy
that's what we're going to do next.
Okay. Um so this equation shows if you
take negative elbow with the assumptions
that we discussed above and construct
your free energy this is how it's going
to look like for pson. So first of all
this reconstruction term is kind of
familiar right you have this mean
squared error that appears because you
chose gausian for your likelihood. So
this this part should be familiar for
all of us. Um if you've seen like you
know predictive coding or or variational
order encoders this part kind of might
look new to you because this this is the
kale term between the approximate
posterior and the prior and for for for
distribution parameterized in its
canonical form which is like the the log
rate um parameterization it's going to
look like this. I mean uh it's it's fine
if you don't really understand this
equation uh right now. Um uh just know
that there's a derivation over here
appendix B3 where I just you know start
from the pulson distribution and derive
this this kale term. So if you're
curious you can check it out there. Uh
what we're going to do is now we're
going to differentiate this f because we
want to derive our dynamics um for the
membrane potentials u.
Okay. Um the first thing is
let's focus on this reconstruction term
here.
So this is an expectation. We want to
differentiate we want to compute this
right? We want to compute the gradient
of f with respect to u because we have u
dot equals
this is our prescription. So I I I told
you in in words but in equations it's
just you know the the rate of change of
your approximate posterior parameters u
is going to be given by the inverse
fissure metric. This is just the fissure
preconditioning. That's what natural
gradient descent means. And the actual
gradient of free energy with respect to
u. So we're going to forget about this
for now. Our focus is to compute this
quantity. Okay. Gradient u of f and f
has two terms. This is the
reconstruction term. This is the kale
term. And we're going to do that
derivation right now. So first off
gradient of this term with respect to u.
Okay. Um, yeah, this is a little bit
difficult because first of all, the U
dependence appears here in the
expectation, right? Let me clean this a
little bit. And you see that this the
whatever is inside here does not depend
on you. It's only in the expectation.
So, we have to also make another
approximation here. And the standard
approximation is that you just take a
single sample. You draw a single sample
from the posterior. And that sample
importantly is going to depend on the
parameter U. And this sample of course
because Q is a plus distribution. This
is just an integer spike count. So it's
a bunch of integers, right? And you plug
that in
and then you say that oh this is my
approximation of the reconstruction
term. Now let's actually compute the
gradient of this instead of that
expectation.
It's technically just a single Monte
Carlo sample
and and then once you do that um you
recognize that you know the chain of
dependence here is that first of all you
have u uh which is the log rate you
exponentiate it to get to the rate and
then you draw a sample to get to this
spider count sample and then you have uh
this reconstruction term as a function
of that z. So we have to apply the chain
rule several times to actually compute
that gradient. So gradient u of uh
reconstruction term is these things um
um you know you have to compute like
three different gradients and here the
gradient of reconstruction term with
respect to z is pretty simple you know
it's just going to look like this you
know it's um 5 transpose * x - 5 z you
know it's very standard um we're going
to leave partial Z to partial R. We're
going we're going to use the straight
through approximation to to just say
that this is this is going to be one.
And then the partial of R with respect
to U is just you know e to the U because
R is X of U. So if you differentiate R
with respect to U, you end up with the
same thing. It's just an exponential.
So with these approximations, the net
result is that we have this expression
for gradient of the reconstruction term.
And now let's go back um and look at the
KL term. It's it's this one is actually
a lot easier. You want to compute the
gradient of this thing with respect to
U. And it's very easy to see that I'm
not going to do it, but it's very easy
to see that this is actually the final
result. So you have e to the u * u minus
u0 and you know u is your posterior
membrane potential u u kn is your prior
because of this blue. So if you just
compine com combine this um
reconstruction gradient with the kl
gradient you end up with this
expression.
Now, now we have the gradient of free
energy with respect to u and then the
last step is to apply this fisser
preconditioning.
Again in appendix B4 I do the derivation
and it turns out if you if you
parameterize a poson distribution in its
canonical log rate uh form the fissure
metric is actually just e to the u
that's just your rate and it amazingly
cancels out this e to the u that
appeared here and you end up with this
final equation.
Okay. So, I I know that I was like being
a little fast, but I just wanted to go
through that real quick so that I can I
can just, you know, interpret the final
result. Okay.
Um,
U dot is how your membrane potential
changes in time to minimize free energy.
That's because we that's, you know, how
we define our dynamics. And whatever
appears on the right hand side is just
that's what the math gave us like the
free energy expression for panon
distributions and all the other
approximations we we made like the Monte
Carlo sample what whatever if you do all
of those you end up with this these
terms and and I want to emphasize we
didn't put any of these in there by hand
it just it was given to us by the
mathematics of uh the free energy with
poson assumptions
but now we're going to interpret those
terms
So what appears here is that there's
this phrpose Xi was you know was our
dictionary element this the transpose of
our decoder and you can think of this as
a feed forward drive because this says
look if you have this image X multiply
it with this like receptive field quote
unquote and then this is going to tell
you how much your membrane potential
should increase given that image X and
then this other term appears that has
this like kind of recurrent term And it
also importantly applies to the spiking
activity from other neurons. It says how
much your um
your membrane potential should drop as a
function of how much you um influence
you receive from other neurons. And
finally, there's this other homeostatic
leak term that says, you know, you just
don't want to deviate too much from your
prior membrane potential. That's what
this term is. And um you know there's an
appendix one of these appendices uh yeah
B5 where I go through like explaining
why we interpret these terms with these
you know phrases like feed forward drive
recurrent explaining away there's
there's a little bit of discussion there
what I want to emphasize here is that
first of all this format of the the
recurrent dynamics equation that that we
ended up deriving from first principles
this is not new this has been studied
from since at least 1970s. There's a
paper from Sunni Amari from like 72 or
something where he explores u properties
of these types of equations and and this
kind of you can think of this as a
canonical circuit model that different
people have studied. Um but
interestingly in our case it just popped
out of the math. We didn't put it any of
these terms by hand. That's what I want
to emphasize here. Um so that's one
thing that's uh pretty interesting.
Another thing I want to emphasize is if
you remember I I told you the predictive
coding equation has certain limitations
in terms of biological plausibility that
uh this equation doesn't. Let me
emphasize that now.
So this is just you know standard
predictive coding dynamics. So u mu dot
is mu is just a another real variable
that you know you can plausibly
interpret as membrane potential
and in predictive coding you also get
this feed forward drive and leak term
and lateral connections term you get all
of them there's there's one important
difference here the influence of other
neurons goes you know the if you
interpret mu as membrane potential these
neurons through these lateral uh like
recurrent connection
influence each other through their
membrane potentials. And we we know that
that's biologically not plausible
because membrane potential of a neuron
is a private signal to that neuron.
You cannot expect that other neurons in
your vicinity to be able to directly be
influenced by your membrane whatever
your membrane potential value is. More
more biologically plausible is that you
know you receive influence from your
neighboring neurons through their
spiking activity.
So remember this and now let's go back
to our equation
whatever we get for poson iterative pos
this is what we get so the the recurrent
in influence comes through spiking
activity and I think that's uh that's a
very interesting um more biologically
plausible outcome that I wanted to
highlight. So you when when when you um
let's say like when you influence your
neighboring neurons through this
recurrent term, it it happens through
your spiking activity, not directly
through your membrane potential.
Okay.
Yeah. Uh I guess here next we just go
from you know continuous time to
discrete time because we want to
implement this. So that's what you see
here. This equation is just a um
discrete time version of that. One last
thing before going to the empirical
results is that um there's some sort of
lateral competition or some sort of
divisive normalization that appears from
from the way we construct this problem.
I want to mention that before going to
the empirical results. Um okay so
remember u is our membrane potentials
right so we defined
u is just log rate.
If you exponentiate this equation which
is are just you know iterative update
rule you get to this equation
which says the rate of a of a neuron at
neuron I at time t + 1 is just its rate
at the previous time point uh modified
with this term that appears here. So,
first of all, there's this feed forward
drive term that says like, you know, if
you're being stimulated through the
stimulus, you can just increase the
firing rate. But there's these other
terms that um stabilize the dynamics
because this says if this W is, by the
way, just a recurrent connectivity
matrix. It says if if two neurons have
overlapping tuning, if they're if they
care about the same feature, you know,
if WIGJ is a positive value, then if
neuron J fires a lot, it's going to
actually silence this other neuron. So
this competition
um is is something that has been
hypothesized to you know to contribute
to many things like you know uh
stability of cortical computation and
and emergence sparity and so on. Um I
just wanted to mention that it just pops
out of our math. Uh also
just because we made like those choices
poson whatever log rate um something
like that appears here. U and and we're
going to see empirically that the
algorithm is stable. It it actually you
know never diverg it it converges beyond
the training regime and so on. So this
is kind of a theoretical reason for
that. But yeah let's just move on
because um we spent too much time on the
theory side. Let me just show you some
experimental results.
So if you train uh if you construct if
you use that um you know the iterative
update rule and then turn that into an
architecture that performs inference
and then train it on natural image
patches.
This is the type of results you can get
like this is the convergence results. So
we trained these models uh using uh 16
training iterations and here we're
comparing uh a posson model with a
gausian model and a gausian plus rail
model. So before actually looking at
these results let let me just mention
what is different between these models.
So um to derive the the theory we just
said look you can choose you can choose
um posan for your for your posterior and
um and that gives you all these like
cool results. But then we don't stop
there. We just say okay but you can also
have gausian for your posterior. You can
still have the same iterative update
through natural gradient descent for
gausian or you can even have gausian and
follow that up with with the relu so
that you get the positivity of of
posson. Um so um these are like a
different different models aim to tease
apart different properties of posson
that that might contribute to its you
know uh performance. So like gausian uh
doesn't have the positivity um of posson
or or its discreetness. Gausian relu has
its positivity but it it's not discrete.
So it's like a continuous positive and
continuous um unsigned.
So that's why we compare these models.
Um so what we have here in this in the
results is that you want to make sure
these models converge um to good
approximate posteriors
and when we measure that using these two
uh measures
we want to have a good reconstruction of
the input that's the R squar uh and it's
you know it's a number between 0 and one
and and larger is better and portion
zeros is the number of zeros in your
representation. So the idea here is that
if you want to represent the world um
you have to represent it in in a very um
highfidelity reconstruction and ideally
using not many active neurons. That's
how you save energy. That's the sparse
coding idea. Therefore we want both the
blue and green curve to be large values
and ignore red for now. Um
and yeah, if you compare these models,
we see that posson has both high
reconstruction and high sparsity. Um
Gausian has the highest reconstruction,
but it's not sparse at all by
definition. And Gausian plus relu gets a
little bit of sparity like little less
than 60%. At around the same uh
reconstruction performance of posan.
Therefore, just the conclusion of this
figure is that it seems like Pson
reconstructs um the images at least as
well as Gausian um um but it you know it
doesn't lose much in the reconstruction
but it this is very sparse. That's the
point of this figure and and also all of
the models converge beyond their
training regime.
And another thing interesting thing to
notice is that after training these
models on natural image patches, you can
visualize the dictionary elements um the
learned decoder and then you can see
that the pan looks like these these
gapors that you would see from you know
if you look at the um the selectivity
from primate visual cortex. Gausian
looks pretty structureless and gausian
learns these like uh pixel-like
representations.
So the conclusion is that um Bosan is
not only more brain-like in this
particular way and also it's more
sparse.
Um in the next figure which is a very
dense one um we want to we want to see
if if that result holds across
hyperparameters. So we do a very large
hyperparameter sweep. Um to understand
this figure first of all let's just
focus on what's on there. Right? First
of all, on the x-axis
we have sparity which we measure as
portion of zeros in your representations
and on the y-axis we have
reconstruction, right? Um so we want to
be ideally here, right? That that's the
impossible to achieve ideal point. You
have maximum reconstruction using no
activation at all. So that's that's hard
to achieve. But the closer you are here
to this point, the better you are. And
we have on here we have all the models
um that we compared to
um we have amotized models. First of all
we have models that have a neural
network encoder and we're going to
compare these amotized models to their
iterative counterparts. And for the
iterative models one thing that I
skipped I didn't mention is that if as
you increase the training um the number
of iterations during training you expect
to see different behavior. But that's
you know a detail that um you can check
out the paper for if you're curious. So
let's focus for now just on the
iterative versus amortized because the
point of this figure is that iterative
inference yields better performance when
you measure performance as like you know
high sparity high reconstruction
like for example in the Pson case the
blue ones you have these are the
iterative models they're kind of having
this burrito front and amotized models
fail to match that performance the the
blue t squares. Um and the idea is that
these you know um amortized models have
like you know deep neural network
encoders with like 6 million parameters
yet they still cannot match the
performance of iterative models. That's
that's a takeaway here
and and same is true for um gausian relu
for example uh these are the iterative
ones these are the amotized ones and for
gausian again the the reconstruction
iterative is better than amotized but
you know um they're not very sparse.
So, so to summarize the this figure
really like panel A we just said okay
let's just take each of these
performances you know each of these
points is is a model with different
hyperparameter
um different beta um and we're going to
compute the ukidian distance between
that and the star and that's the summary
over here and here lower is better
we see that first of all the first
observation we have is that in all of
these cases iterative model is better
than its amortized counterpart. So one
thing one takeaway here is that if you
have an amortized neural network encoder
and your model is not performing well
it's possible that it's because you know
the of the amortization gap which is a
technical term that means like you you
don't you're fail you're failing to find
the optimal posterior through that
neural network and and iterative post
does uh best you know uh compared to
these models and also So LCA this
locally competitive algorithm which is a
sparse coding algorithm does also as
good as iterative post on VAVE. So one
conclusion we draw from here is that um
yeah I I I kind of skipped this because
you know uh it's too much details but
that the equation we derive for
iterative plus VAE uh looks very much
like the equation for LCA. Therefore, we
can conclude that iterative panvia is
just like, you know, LCA, but it's a
spiking stochastic version of it. That's
one of the um takeaways.
Uh but yeah, so these are the two main
results that we report in the main paper
and we just run out of space basically.
But there's a bunch of you know um
uh appendix results that are also
equally interesting. So let me just
really quickly go through them.
Yeah. So if you want to read the
appendex you can this is the extended
back extended background just you know
all all you need to understand this
paper. Then there's extended theory
where we extend the pson derivations to
uh to Gausian and to nonlinear decoders
and so on. Um,
and there's all sorts of other uh
information if you're curious. And then
extended experiments um where we explore
other other properties of the model. Um,
yeah, I want to show you this one.
Where is it?
Yeah. So we have these out of
distribution generalization results that
I think are equally interesting but we
just didn't have space so we put them in
the appendex. Um what is out of
distribution generalization? Um
if you train your your models on some
data set and then you test it some in
some other data set if those two data
sets are you know sufficiently different
then usually what you get from machine
learning models is that they fail to
generalize. That's a typical uh failure
mode of machine learning models. But if
you have iterative inference, we're
going to find that um that's really not
the case in in in our iterative poson.
So that's that's the point of these
results. What we do is we train models
on Nest here
and then test it on out of distribution
um you know data sets like you know
extended MNST which is just uh character
data set uh omniots and even imageet 32
so grayscaleed cropped versions of
natural images and also we tested on
rotated emnest
and we also compared to alternative uh
models you know as as we briefly we
discussed. Uh there's there are hybrid
iterative amortized models such as uh
iterative amortized VAE. This is the
Marino paper 2018. There's another one
semi-amortized VAE uh also from 2018 um
where they start where they initialize
the posterior with an amortized uh
network and then they perform stocastic
variational inference a few iterative
updates on that initial amortized guess
and we're going to compare to those two.
Um our model is fully iterative. There's
no neural network at all. Uh but these
two models are hybrid and and we want to
find out if um hybrid models perform as
well on these kind of OD tasks and and
the the spoiler alert. No, the answer is
no. Um iterative wins basically.
So this is um I think too much detail.
I'm going to skip that. Let me just show
you this result. So
what we have here, let's just focus on
this panel. We trained the all of these
models including iterative poson v
amortized PVA right this is iterative
poson uh this is amortized PVA this is
amortized iterative there's a
hierarchical and and single layer
version and this is semiotized we're
going to compare all of these models in
this task of you have these emnest
digits all of these models were trained
on this standard MNEST data set which is
the first row and then we're going to
rotate the digits by 90°. And we're
going to look at two things, you know,
um compared to the rotated digits, the
original ground truth. Um amortized
poson fails really bad. It it just it
doesn't, you know, reconstruct any of
these digits.
And among the uh the hybrid models that
we compare to, semivertised does the
best um out of those three. And if you
quantify this on the right hand side
over here
um we find that you know iterative bos
does best. Um the first figure uh this
one is reconstruction where we report
mean square error and the x-axis is just
the amount of rotation we apply and this
other figure is just a classification
accuracy. So that this is important
because you know um if it was just
reconstruction you know who knows like
if if the model really understands the
data. I mean okay sure in this for examp
this this is a 90° task. Um sure we see
that in the reconstruction we see
um bosan does best. It's the lowest
reconstruction error but you know it
could be just the shallow features of of
the data set. you know it it doesn't
mean that this model has has learned to
actually understand the semantic meaning
of this data and that we confirm by by
looking at the classification. But this
is downstream classification uh when
when we just show these images to the
model and uh extract the final posterior
and we train um logistic regression to
just classify those rotated digits. It
it turns out that the performance of the
iterative plus on the blue bars it
doesn't drop. It's it it remains flat.
But as the task gets harder and harder,
all the other models go down and up. So
this indicates that it actually learns
to interpret the distorted data in not
only uh well enough to reconstruct it,
but also well enough to be able to
classify those rotated digits.
Um and and I think there's there's other
experiments that I'm going to skip.
There's too much. Um I think this is the
I think it's pretty crazy result. Um
here we just say okay let's just take
mnest digits rotate you know um crop
them and and make them grayscaled
because you know um sorry um yeah these
are for im imageet 32x32 but we're
cropped so that they they're um
this center image is is where there's
variance in uh mnest digits. So
and if you if you show these inputs to
the model and then let them perform
inference across time as you see the the
iterative pos starts to actually
reconstruct these images that you can
recognize this is a panda this is a dog
and so on even though this model the
iterative poson I want to I want to
emphasize this this was trained on
emnest it hasn't seen any natural images
yet it can reconstruct them and all the
other models including the semi-averized
you know um they don't do as well and I
mean this model it amortized iterative
just does you know the worst none of
these reconstructions look anything like
the actual image the semiiamortized does
decently well but not as good as
iterative pos
um and of course we also quantify that
here so we have the number of iterations
at test time and reconstruction error on
on these cropped natural images. And
there's really two things to notice in
this figure. The first thing to notice
is the final performance. It's just much
better than all of these other models.
That's one thing. But equally
interesting to me is that the model
actually keeps improving as time goes
on. you know it's the the other models
they don't improve as much or you know
they even diverge at the end but
iterative pos keeps improving and that
that shows that it it's you know
basically you can interpret this as like
it's thinking more and more to to to be
able to understand this difficult data
set out of distribution data set
um and and why is that we provide one
possible explanation for why this out of
domain generalization happens through
this visual visualization. So if you
visualize the learned decoder weight for
the last layer of this iterative poson
va it learns gabors from mnest I'm sorry
yeah from mnest um these are you know
primitive kind of like universal
features that you can construct any
image from these and iterative poson v
learns those gibbors the poson v is the
same latent distribution same integer
whatever sparse representation but with
a NLP encoder it just learns these like
digits like ghost digits that it doesn't
really learn any any gavors um so the
conclusion is that if you have a model
that learns these universal features and
it has an inference algorithm that can
utilize those universal features it's
going to be able to reconstruct any data
set even as crazy as you know grayscale
corrupt natural images. So that's the
conclusion for these uh OD results in
page 58 of of the appendix. But you know
um we the reason we put this in the
appendix is that um I think this is a
very cool result and it it just warrants
more deeper exploration and even like in
you know in tasks beyond uh
reconstruction. I suspect that with this
iterative inference algorithm, the model
learns um compositional features that
allows this generalization and and we
want to test that on more difficult
tasks, more more involved task than
reconstruction so that we can explore it
u give it the attention that it
deserves.
But yeah, that's that's pretty much it.
And you know, there's a extended
discussion too, which I think there's
really no time to go through. But I hope
that um this was actually interesting
enough for you to actually go read the
paper because uh there's a lot more in
the paper that I just simply couldn't
talk about. It's just um
too much. Um but yeah, with that, I'm
happy to take questions.
Great.
That last
reconstruction was awesome.
Thank you. Very cool. Uh in the image of
the child,
it almost looked like like the fingers
of the like the the the base image was
it almost looks like the child has
extended their fingers.
Yeah, this one is a little creepier.
Yeah. Um Yeah. Very cool. Yeah. Kevin
just wrote nice result and figures
emergence of the primitives rather than
overfitting. Yeah. Like and seeing the
seeing the ghost digits in the emnest.
It's kind of like yeah we we know we can
pull out the template of a digit from
overlaying a bunch of copies of the
digit and just looking for sort of like
the k means clustering of what does the
archetypal representative look like? But
to be able to do it the way that the
visual system algorithmically
does, extracting with the lateral uh
relationships amongst layers to pull out
the edges is is the kind of neuromorphic
transfer.
Yeah.
Um okay, I'll ask some of the questions
in the live chat. Anyone else can can
write. Um Okay.
Hi. asks, "Does this architecture solve
catastrophic forgetting?"
Okay, we we haven't tested that. So, I
think my understanding of catastrophic
catastrophic forgetting is that you
train the model on some task and then
you retrain it. You change the model
parameters on a new task and it it fails
to work on the first task you trained
on. We haven't really explored that. Um
and and by the way this this this model
is is fairly uh underparameterized. Um
it just has a decoder and therefore I
expect that if you train it on one task
and then you know train it on another
task it might actually have some sort of
uh catastrophic forgetting. Uh but um
yeah I haven't I haven't really
experimented with that. So I just don't
know.
Okay little curveball question. Are you
on the Active Inference Institute
Discord?
I am not. I should join. Okay, I'll I'll
put in the chat or afterwards a join
link. That would be cool though.
Definitely. Yes. Okay. Um there was one
question about this relates to the
lateral relationships amongst neurons.
You mentioned that the membrane
potential is a private variable. So how
do we think about um and not that the
goal of the model was to give a
mechanistic account of neural tissue but
how would you account for non-neural
cell types like gal cells or like local
field potentials?
Mhm. Mhm. Okay. Yeah. I think I should
uh highlight here that you know um one
of the words we used in the title of
this paper brain like you know it's it's
a very interesting word because
I think it's true to some extent. This
model is brain-like in the following
ways. Okay. So, it uses discrete and
sparse representations that's relatively
more brain-like than Gausian. It uses
iterative inference that gets better and
better over time. It also you can uh you
know hypothetically we can think that's
more brain like even though that's not
it's not settled. We don't really know.
Maybe brain is actually more amortized
iterative hybrid in a in a sense but
it's really not brain like in terms of
these biological details. So
like even this recurrent explaining away
like okay for example another important
way in which this model is not brain
like is that there are no explicitly
inhibitory neurons. If you look at these
biologically plausible circuit models uh
that people in computational
neuroscience have been working with,
they have explicit uh population of
neurons that are excitatory and
inhibitory and they have you know
different um they exhibit different
behaviors and and so on that is missing
from this model let alone ga right so I
think that it's
yeah it's relatively more brain-like
than let's say a gausian model, but it's
still far from being brain like in a
true and full sense of the term.
So, in the posttock phase, you're in
like looking back on some of these
pretty theoretically synthetic but also
implementably useful techniques that
you've been working on with colleagues.
like what are you looking to next or
what kinds of work are you going to turn
to now?
Okay, that's uh um I I think that I
really want to emphasize the engineering
aspect these days. I want to make model
that work on real data sets. So this
paper is pretty theor theoryheavy. I
guess just let's let's derive things
from first principles and it works on
toy data sets. It works on natural image
patches. It works on enlist. It
generalizes. All of these are very um um
I would say preliminary but but but you
know um highly encouraging results that
shows that this model might actually
work on real data sets. So right now I'm
exploring many different directions like
one of them is um in this particular
paper we talk about you know an online
update scheme where your posterior at
time t literally becomes your prior at
t+1. There's no predictive dynamics.
There's no anticipatory dynamics where
you evolve the posterior to become the
next prior. I think that's a key missing
piece that uh and without that it's not
going to work on videos. you know we've
only trained this on natural images like
static images repeated many times that's
one thing I'm working on um predictive
component and and this model had a
single layer it's not hierarchical but
we know that you know from predictive
coding and I have another paper from two
years ago that hierarchical inference is
has many benefits and and if I want to
make this work on real data sets like a
video it should have hierarchical latent
structure so these are two directions.
Uh I think they're related, but
independent directions like predictive
component and hierarchical architecture
is what I'm pushing this toward. One
last thing that I'm actually pretty
excited about these days is that, you
know, this out of domain generalization
is is a big big challenge in robotics.
you know, people train their robots in
some, you know, in some environment and
when you test those robots in some
slightly different environment, even
even just like simple luminance change
and things like that breaks the the
perception algorithm of those those
robots. And because I have these like
very promising OD results, I'm hoping
that I can beef up this model and then
show that it actually uh helps address
some of those very difficult challenges
in robotics, especially when it comes to
OD. So just to summarize, predictive
component hierarchical robotics.
Awesome. Just while we're right here,
could you say a little bit about the
natural aspect and what does Fisher
preconditioning do? Like what values are
being transformed or conditioned? How
and then how would you say that relates
to whether something is like natural?
I think I'm just borrowing that term
from you know the literature natural
gradient descent. you if you just look
at the uh Amari's papers or like you
know recent reviews of that that's just
how you define natural gradient descent
and what is so natural about it is just
it it respects the intrinsic geometry of
the you know parameter space I can go
back to this figure here so you know we
have okay um now we have you know u if
you remember we have these we have these
membrane potentials that's our state
space and this curve red curve here is
just how you evolve a posterior
distribution. Like each point literally
is just a posterior distribution through
this operation. you exponentiate you
construct a poson distribution from each
point and it's not an ukidian space in
the sense that if you want to go from
here to here and this is like one unit
of distance it might be different if you
go in this other direction and I think
it's actually if you want to if you want
to understand why it's important um why
do we have to have this like
preconditioning for specifically for for
inference. I'm going to actually find
the references uh to point you to
because they do a lot better job than I
can do in this um uh to to motivate
that. So, I'm going to actually just do
it right now cuz I think this is
actually this is this is not appreciated
enough in the in the literature. So, um
it's important thing.
First of all, if you want to appreciate
why natural gradient, definitely check
this out. The Beijian learning rule is
is a great paper and this Amari paper is
of course you know um it's the canonical
like the original original paper that
talks about that and there's this
there's another paper from MTS Khan from
2018 I I think I do cite it but I I
might not be able to find it right now
um that is like four or five page paper
where they they show some figures and
they they discuss the intuition why
natural gradient is so central and
important especially if you're doing um
if you're doing inference. There we go.
Start with this. Check out this paper.
Uh it's five-page paper and and they
they provide an intuition why um
computing distances in the distribution
space and computing uh or doing like uh
stochastic gradient descent in the
distribution space is not ideal. You
have to do uh natural gradient descent
to respect the intrinsic geometry
and intrinsic geometry should be
respected.
Exactly.
Anything else you want to add? This was
awesome though and I think gives a lot
of technical details and and really
useful aspects.
Well yeah thanks for having me. I mean I
um I always enjoy these discussions and
um I guess if you have any questions you
can find me you know you can email me
here you can check out the code and uh
yeah that's it. Cool. Uh I put the
Discord link in the chat if you want to
join or you can uh find other ways and
uh see you in one year.
Definitely. Yes. Looking forward to it.
Okay. Thank you. Bye. Okay. Thanks
again. Bye.